Register of the Socialist Workers Party Records, 1928-2002
Wisconsin Historical Society
- Part 1 (Micro 596, Micro 816, Micro 993, Micro 1078, Micro 2015, Micro 2050, AC 588, CB 131): Original Collection, 1928-1993, Micro 596; 185 reels of microfilm (35mm) and 2 films
  Additional information on the SWP's educational program may be found in the papers of George Novack and Bob Chester, also in custody of the Wisconsin Historical Society.
  Election Files
  This series documents the SWP's national election campaigns from 1948 to 1988. Coverage varies, with the elections of the 1950s only sparsely covered, and the elections of the 1970s being extensively represented. Information on party participation in local election campaigns has been incorporated with the branch records described below. Following the information on individual elections is material on the Election and Referenda Subcommittee of the Political Committee.
  The election files generally consist of press releases, form letters distributed to local organizers, brochures and campaign literature, and--less often--national campaign committee correspondence, minutes, and reports. The most useful documentation for each campaign generally can be found in the files of press material because the contents (press releases, form correspondence, clippings, flyers, and occasional speeches) provide the most comprehensive chronological overview. Undated campaign literature, flyers, and buttons are filed separately. Except for this material and the form letters to local supporters, documentation about the development of national electoral policy is limited. Only a few campaigns are represented by National Campaign Committee minutes, and the majority of the correspondence files appear incomplete. Among the most useful correspondence are the letters from Fred Halstead and Barry Sheppard during their 1968 tour of Vietnam, Japan, and other overseas areas and the reports of Presidential candidate Linda Jenness.
  Branch Correspondence
  The branch office files are organized alphabetically by branch name and document type, with several of the most important branches also being divided by district. For each branch, minutes and reports are arranged first if they were maintained as a distinct and separate file by the SWP; they are followed by chronologically-arranged correspondence and publications. Holdings of branch minutes are generally incomplete, although some branches regularly submitted such documentation to the national office. The majority of the branch publications are discussion bulletins containing editorials by local SWP members, newspapers or fact sheets and general information on local and national activities. If they are numerous, branch newsletters are arranged by title. For less complete titles the publications are interfiled with the correspondence.
  Most of the branch correspondence consists of exchanges between the locals and the national office. This correspondence covers a wide range of topics depending on the particular circumstances of the branch. These files also vary in completeness. Most extensively documented are Chicago, Cleveland, Detroit, Los Angeles, Minneapolis, New York City, San Francisco, and Seattle. Several branch files provide important documentation on party history during the 1940s. A common trait of the branch records is a gradual increase over time in the number of leaflets, flyers, minutes, reports, and local election campaign literature, and a decrease in regular correspondence. In some files, the material on the 1970s consists almost completely of nearprint publications.
  Activities and Organizing Records
  These files document the SWP's focused outreach and party building work. The files are grouped alphabetically by subject.
  Anti-nuclear power work is a small file consisting primarily of circulars distributed to National Committee members and organizers, and later to anti-nuclear work directors. The file dates from 1977 to 1982.
  The Anti-Vietnam War file is also small, documenting only a portion of the SWP's leadership in the opposition to the war in Vietnam. In fact, this file largely consists of folders that the party itself entitled a policy file. The file is only a small portion of the material that is available to researchers on this topic elsewhere in this collection as well as in separately-cataloged collections of Fred Halstead, the Young Socialist Alliance, and the Student Mobilization Committee--all of which were also donated to the Historical Society by the Socialist Workers Party. The miscellaneous antiwar materials filed here consist of SWP and YSA branch circulars that deal with opposition to the war in Vietnam. Many of the circulars originally filed here when the records were received from the SWP had already been filmed more appropriately as part of the minutes and circulars elsewhere in the collection. As a consequence, this file consists only of documents that could not be located elsewhere.
  The Anti-Draft Registration work file is a small quantity of material which dates only from 1980 to 1985.
  The Defense cases work deals primarily with court cases and legal matters with which the SWP was involved and some material on cases in which they were interested although not actively involved (i.e. the small files on Angela Davis and Kathy Boudin). The majority of the files date from the 1960s and 1970s. Generally, the files have been arranged alphabetically by keyword, with some larger files also subdivided by genre. The files may variously contain correspondence, form letters, publicity, legal documents, and clippings. Most of the correspondence consists of exchanges between the SWP national office (and the YSA national staff) and the committees formed to deal with the litigation. On the whole, the cases cover a wide range of political and social issues, particularly freedom of speech, academic freedom, and anti-SWP violence. Some of the high profile cases documented here include those of the Monroe, North Carolina, civil rights complainants; Morris Starsky and Wendell Phillips (academic freedom at Arizona State University and Fullerton Junior College); and Babak Zahrair, Ernest Mandel, and Hector Marroquin (all concerning the rights of aliens). Considerable material documents the free speech rights of students on various Florida campuses. In addition, there is documentation about various episodes of harassment experienced by SWP locals and the political assassination of Leo Bernard, an SWP member, as well as the organization of the Committee for Democratic Election Rights to ensure the rights of party members to campaign for elective office. Numerous folders concern the party's defense of the First Amendment rights of active duty GIs who opposed the war in Vietnam such as Howard Petrick, Joe Miles, Jim Stryffler, Walter Kos, and the Jackson Eight.
  The Gay rights files are another artificial category assembled by the SWP national office to document the party's activities in a special area. This file, which primarily documents the years 1971-1979, is comprised of correspondence, reports, and clippings. The 1971 file is dominated by a probe of gay rights activities in various branches conducted by the national organization. Notable in the 1974 materials are documents relating to the actions of David Thorstad, who resigned from the party because of its failure to support the gay liberation movement.
  The International Solidarity files contain articles, correspondence, and miscellaneous documents on the party's involvement in, support for, and awareness of political movements around the globe. The files are ordered alphabetically by country, and they generally date from the 1960s and 1970s, although some files on the plight of European party members and refugees date from the immediate post-World War II years. It is likely this small file represents only a portion of the party's involvement in international issues. It is difficult from these records to determine the party's role in some organizations [such as the Committee for Artistic and Intellectual Freedom in Iran (CAIFI)]. On the whole, the files suggest that the party considered that intellectual freedom was essential to the working class and the continuation of the international socialist revolution. The files suggest that the SWP focused much of its international attention on poor countries such as South Africa where social inequality was prevalent and the government suppressed leftist political dissent. For example, the party attacked the Mexican government's crackdown on communists in the late 1960s, and it supported groups such as the CAIFI that protested against the Shah's treatment of Iranian radicals and intellectuals in the 1970s. Moreover, the party remained concerned about freedom of political expression and criticized limitations on student, intellectual, and worker protest in more powerful and self-sufficient nations such as France and Greece. The SWP paid particular attention to the plight of blacks and the detention of intellectuals in South Africa in the mid-1960s. Finally, while the SWP focused on the internal politics of other nations, it also criticized the United States for aiding countries such as Angola and Israel that engaged in political oppression.
  Particularly interesting are the World War II-era files on the American Committee for European Workers Relief, which was headed by Dr. Antoinette Konikow, and the American Funds for Political Prisoners and Refugees, both of which are represented by correspondence, financial reports, and publications. The small file on oppression in post-World War II Greece is primarily documented by a campaign to get support from many prominent American leftists for a letter opposing press censorship in Greece. There are only a few responses to this appeal in the file, most interesting being letters from Dwight Macdonald and Harry Fleischman of the Socialist Party. The papers on Iran consist of CAIFI press releases, newsletters, and form letters and a transcription of a Kate Millet press conference in 1974. Papers on South Africa are extensive, with the majority of this being devoted to the Alexander Defense Committee and to publicity tours by I.B. Tabata and others. With the International Solidarity materials are special files about the SWP's relations with two separate organizations also concerned with international issues: the Fair Play for Cuba Committee and the U.S. Committee for Justice to Latin American Political Prisoners.
  The Fair Play for Cuba Committee file consists of organizational records collected by the SWP. Included are correspondence, handbills, chapter releases, publicity, reprints, and clippings. Newsletters both of the national organization and several local chapters are available through the SHSW Library. The most extensively documented local FPFC groups are those from California, Canada, Michigan, and New York City. The majority of the correspondence consists of exchanges between Tom Kerry and Farrell Dobbs and with local SWP members who were active in the committee. This correspondence contains a good deal of information about local activites and the SWP's desire to be involved in the Cuba issue. There is some correspondence with Berta Greene, apparently an SWP member, who was at one time the FPFC secretary, and with founder Robert Taber.
  The USLA Justice Committee was formed in 1966 to aid the victims of political persecution and injustice in Latin America and to inform the American public about these repressive policies. This file, which may have been collected by Richard Garza, a member of the SWP who served on the USLA board, consists mainly of chronologically-arranged press material, form letters, and flyers. Best documented are the years 1972 to 1974. Mimeographed minutes of a few meetings and conferences are also included.
  The Oppressed Nationalities files document the party's political work among African-Americans and, to a much lesser extent, among Latinos, Chicanos, and Puerto Ricans. Although the work among Blacks began early in the party's history, the records from this period are very incomplete and they primarily document activities during the 1960s and 1970s. The records are arranged in two sections: a chronological file pertaining to general organizational work among Blacks and an alphabetical subject file documenting work on particular topics or with individual organizations. Among the well represented organizations are the National Black Independent Political Party, the Freedom Now Party, and the Black Panther Party.
  The general files consist of correspondence, reports, circulars, and occasional minutes. This documentation probably does not represent the full extent of SWP involvement in the Black struggle, although the material spans the period from 1942 to 1987. The early documentation includes the resolution on negro work adopted by the 1939 national convention, a 1956 letter to Martin Luther King enclosing a $75.00 contribution, correspondence pertaining to William Worthy and the Freedom Now Party, and 1967 minutes of the Black Fraction in New York. Beginning in the mid-1960s the file begins to be dominated by branch circulars and mimeographed reports from the national office to national committee members and later to the local individuals responsible for antiracist work. This type of documentation ends in 1979, although some correspondence continues through 1987.
  On the whole, the general files reflect the SWP's uncertain attempts to address the rising black consciousness of the 1960s and 1970s and wed the black power movement, represented by such groups as the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, the Freedom Now Party, the Negro American Labor Council, the African Liberation Support Committee, the Congress on Racial Equality, and the black muslims, with the labor struggle. Recognizing many shared interests with these groups, the SWP championed busing, school desegregaion, and freedom for oppressed minorities in South Africa and Angola throughout the 1970s. In 1975, the party advocated the first National Student Conference Against Racism in Boston and actively supported formation of the Student Coalition Against Racism the following year. In the 1980s a new generation of leaders, including Malik Miah, a member of the SWP Political Committee and National Office staffer, and Maceo Dixon, the SWP national Black work director, and Osborne Hart, the YSA national Black work director, continued to wrestle with the question of how the black movement could bolster the workers' struggle.
  The alphabetical subject files within the oppressed minorities files include three undated lectures prepared by Robert Vernon on the evolution of the SWP position on Black nationalism. The documentation about the Black Panthers includes documentation similar to the general files. Particularly notable are the transcriptions of the joint SWP-BPP discussions and the August 17-18, 1968 National Committee meeting which led to SWP support of some BPP candidates in San Francisco area elections. There is also an edited transcript of the discussions in the Oakland branch which eventually led to SWP endorsement of some BPP candidates in the 1973 elections in that community. Several other black political groups are documented in the subject files, particularly the Freedom Now Party, the National Black United Front, and the Congress of Afrikan Peoples.
  The SWP remained concerned, however, not only with the situation of Black Americans, but other oppressed minorities as well and the records include some material on the Chicano movement as well as on Puerto Rican, Latino, and Native American poltical groups. The file on the Crusade for Justice, for instance, documents the violence which broke out between the SWP and the Chicano movement led by Rodolfo Corky Gonzalez in Denver in 1974. The Latino liberation file combines documentation on work with Puerto Ricans, Latinos, and Chicanos that was chiefly carried out by Olga Rodriquez of the SWP national office and it highlights the SWP's interest in Puerto Rican independence. The file on Native Americans concerns the American Indian Movement (AIM) and its leader, Dennis Banks. While these files contain interesting and, at times, revealing information, their content is questionable.
  Information about the NBIPP, however, with which the SWP had increasingly troubled relations during the early 1980s, includes an extensive reference file of NBIPP convention and meeting minutes, discussion and policy papers, clippings, brochures and press materials on both the national organization and a few of its many local chapters, and speeches and writings of Manning Marable and other party leaders, together with a file of memoranda and correspondence that focuses on the SWP's internal response to the black political party. The NBIPP file is of uncertain provenance. Although described by the SWP as the NBIPP records when they were donated to the Historical Society, these documents clearly are not official records. It is more likely these records were collected by Mac Warren, who headed SWP black organizing at the time. This provenance possibly explains why few files are complete and why coverage diminishes after the break with the SWP.
  The reference portion of the records is further subdivided into four sections: background information, convention and meetings, subject files, and local files. The background material consists of some national recruiting material that includes a brief history of the party. The national party conventions and Central Committee meetings which are also documented here are the best represented aspects of NBIPP history. The convention and meeting files, which are arranged chronologically by date, consist of flyers, minutes, agendas, resolutions and amendments, documents submitted for discussion, publicity, and other items that related to various national, regional and local gatherings of the party and its Central Committee and the Administrative and Policy Committee. The subject files, which are more diverse in content, are alphabetically-arranged. Of special interest is a small file on NBIPP's relationship with the SWP and a collection of documents gathered by Mac Warren about NBIPP history which include his comments on the meaning of particular documents. Also present is a chronological file of clippings about the party and several newsletters.
  The local files are an artificial assemblage of mailings concerning the activities of NBIPP chapters. These files document only a few of 100 local chapters which once existed and only a few chapters are documented by more than a few items. However, several files (primarily Baltimore, Los Angeles, New York, and Ohio) contain information on activities carried on during the last year's of NBIPP's existence.
  The Trade Union files, although similar to the other organizing records in the SWP collection, are primarily comprised of original correspondence rather than the mimeographed circulars that typify most other files. The trade union files are also unusual in that the majority of documentation here dates from the 1940's, before declining in quantity to parallel the party's diminished interest in labor work in later years. The trade union files are differentiated into a general chronological file followed by an alphabetical fraction file. However, the same types of documentation appear in both files. Both contain detailed summaries of local labor union matters and the activities of local party members. Virtually all of the post World War II correspondence contains some evidence of redbaiting, as well as detailed accounts of the conflicts that took place between local Stalinist, Trotskyist, and conservative union leaders. The material dating from the 1940's consists mainly of correspondence to and from various SWP leaders who served as labor secretary during the decade: Farrell Dobbs, Vincent R. Dunne, and Bert Cochran, together with considerable correspondence of Murray Stein, who served as acting national secretary while Cannon was in prison. The early correspondence represents relatively complete, organic files, but after 1950 that is not the case. Instead, the later records document sporadic episodes of involvement in union elections and democratic insurgency within labor unions. A few small files from the 1940's appear to represent segments of the labor force that were not organized into SWP fractions.
  The early material in the general trade union files is largely concerned with the SWP's position in relation to the CIO. The correspondence here primarily documents the years from 1940 to 1945 and the year 1974. The early letters are to and from Farrell Dobbs and Murray Stein; while the 1974 letters, most of which are incoming, provide the most comprehensive representation in the trade union files about Frank Lovell's tenure as labor secretary.
  Best documented among the alphabetical fraction files are those on the United Automobile Workers, electrical workers, the maritime unions, the United Steelworkers of America, and the Teamster. The automobile fraction files, which are most extensive for the period 1943 to 1951, contain extensive information on union elections and the development of SWP's opposition to Reuther in 1947. The more recent material about the auto fraction consists of literature about an insurgent candidacy within Local 600 in 1963 (this is unsupported by any correspondence), and some 1970-1971 SWP circulars. Notable in the electrical fraction is postwar correspondence to labor secretary Bert Cochran about the Trotskyists position on local UE-IUE rivalries. The files on the maritime fraction are best on the immediate postwar years. Here may be found numerous excellent summaries of working conditions within various segments of the industry. There is also a large file of handbills and brochures distributed by the Joint Action Committee of the Maritime Unions during the 1948 strike in San Francisco.
  The files on the United Steel Workers are also excellent. In addition to documentation that is similar to the fractions described above there is also good information on the SWP's industry-wide steel conference (1945) and on the democratic Steelworkers Fight Back campaign of insurgent leader Ed Sadlowsky to reform the USWA. Early files on the railroad unions are not as useful as many of the other fraction files, although there is some excellent material from UTU member Ed Heisler in 1971 on the Right to Vote campaign. The Teamster files represent Dobbs' special background in the truck drivers' interests and much of the 1940-1941 correspondence concerns individuals in the midwest (and particularly in Minneapolis) whom he knew from his former Teamster organizing. The correspondence from Vincent R. Dunne and other former Minneapolis associates is particularly revealing of the campaign waged by Daniel Tobin to oust them from leadership in the local Teamsters. Important among the postwar Teamster material is information on the democratic movement in St. Louis in 1947.
  Historical Files
  These records divide into two portions: File 1, a Chronological File, and File 2, an Organizational File. The two contain similar material that is differently arranged.
  Chronological File 1 is an artificial file created to encompass a variety of documentation that eluded filing elsewhere. Most of the documents were arranged in this category by the SWP, although a few miscellaneous items were later added in the SHSW Archives. The entire file is arranged chronologically by year (or by initial year for the files that include multi-year time spans). The earliest files consist of documents regarding organizations that preceded or related to the SWP. Documentation after 1938 primarily relates to the SWP itself and, to some extent, to YSA.